welcome this is an addendum to the
series awakening from the meaning crisis
recently I released an episode on young
as a prophet of the meaning crisis I
decided it would it be a good idea to
have my good friend and colleague
Anderson Todd he's a former student of
mine and that was a colleague of mine we
worked together he's the associate
director of the consciousness of wisdom
studies lab he has a degree in cognitive
science he's also studied young
extensively he's a practicing
psychotherapist so I thought it would be
a very good idea to bring Anderson in
and bring this into a more of a dialogue
format and talk about young the meaning
crisis and how that intersects with
other thinkers like Corbin and current
thinkers like Jordan Peterson so
Anderson welcome very much welcome well
thanks Ryan I'm happy to be here so I
came to young quite early I think as
many people do I came to young sort of
obliquely through sort of cultural
products you know he's hidden on the
cover of Sergeant peppers in the
background so you know I kept
encountering him the music of the police
but I didn't have a very clear sense of
it and then I began to read young when I
was 12 or 13 and like things that I was
reading around the time I was reading
Freud as well and there is a there's a
big difference you know Freud is very
loose in writer right and so although I
you know just grieve with a great deal
of what Freud rode and sort of the
theory doesn't always hold up for me
although he's a giant the theory doesn't
always hold up for me nevertheless it
has that lucid and quality right so
reading at page by page it's very
compelling and reading Jung was not like
that it was very difficult so I would
sort of wade through it and it would be
like slogging through mud and I would
hit these long passages like written in
Greek and but nevertheless every page or
two I would hit sort of a jewel and
stumble on something like this that just
sort of stopped me in my tracks you know
a single sentence or a single paragraph
that seemed to connect really really
deeply to my felt experience of things
and so Jung came to have sort of a
an increasingly central role in the way
that I was structuring thinking around
psychology in my in my kind of teenage
years
and then I dropped it and and came back
to it as one does with these things and
sort of went back and forth periodically
making like a deeper and deeper slog
into the collected works and I worked as
a full-time writer for quite a few years
as a as a novelist and nonfiction mm-hmm
and it's sort of hard to avoid the
archetypal especially if you read people
like Northup Frye right if you're
interested in critical theory although
northrup are actually never credits
young he did have highly imitated copies
of yumminess I didn't know that he'd
never credits him never no in fact he
deliberately kind of rejects and slags
on him I mean Young was sort of persona
non grata in the Academy and to some
extent still is right so you know I was
encountering these ideas more deeply and
and giving thought to them and when I
eventually came to university I had it
in mind to eventually work towards being
a psychotherapist which is what I now do
and had something of a depth
psychological framework in mind so that
kind of psychodynamic approach to
thinking about people's to thinking
about people's problems in the way that
personality forms and development and so
on and so forth was very central for me
but even then I felt that there were
pretty deep
problems with it so some of those are
reasonably well known you know you know
died in the 60s and so you know lots of
his ideas which may at one time have had
some currency you know really are in
pretty bad need of updating and you know
in other areas like every other thinker
he's at least 50% wrong and that became
sort of increasingly obvious to me where
he gets things right he's it's striking
and shocking and he's a very talented
phenomenologist and I think he was a
remarkably talented clinician in some
ways but also you know there are big
gaps in his theory there are pieces
where he struggles to articulate things
and doesn't really have a scientific
language at hand to do so he does sort
of the best he can with you know quantum
mechanics in places and it doesn't quite
work
but then also you know the the blind
spots that just come about with the fact
that you know he's contrary to what the
Jungian community often I think treats
it he's not a saint you know he's a man
and he's a human being and one with you
know his own fairly deep character flaws
so the desire to sort of supplement his
work started to take on more and more
importance to me and then when I got to
university yeah when I got to university
as it turns out I already knew you
weirdly so I had I had audited your
classes like back in the 90s because
friends of mine who are enrolled at the
school were doing cognitive science
degree and because I didn't realize yet
that I wanted to be part of the Academy
I just spent all of my time with
students and in the library I ended up
auditing a bunch of your classes and I
don't think you remember this we had an
argument of a leprechaun's
where I was being I think a bit of a I
think I was being a bit of a like
intellectual saboteur you were
explaining something I said you know
something we could explain that with
leprechauns and I remember you giving me
like a really I don't
are you serious look I actually feel
like that that's a really good note for
things anyway so so yeah so we had met
then and had a few encounters and so
when I first took your course on I think
cognitive science and Buddhism I think
is the first course I took with you that
pretty rapidly got me to swing my major
I had been doing an English major out of
a simple desire to do something
straightforward and I pretty rapidly
dropped that and did cog sigh and it was
not long thereafter I think that you and
I started to collaborate so
collaborating on the work around
consciousness and then I think soon
thereafter was when we started talking
about the lab and a few other projects
and of course you you were a speaker
right from the outset as were a few
other people Tony Tony Otto Dan told
Herman Jordan Pederson we're all
speakers at the conference series that I
started yeah ah yeah mine manners which
ran for six six years mm-hmm yeah so
yeah so in that time you know we you you
and I had sort of an increasing number
of collaborations but also I had spent
the better part of that period trying to
sort of
wrestle these different interests I had
in the mind into some kind of working
synthesis and I sensed that it was
possible to do so and that's still sort
of an ongoing project and it's a tricky
one because you know the the sort of
driving ethos of cognitive science you
know you would make the argument
generally and certainly here at the
University of Toronto is this commitment
to the naturalistic imperative yes but I
was once asked by somebody really early
on why why young at Toni Toni Otto
actually yeah I said and I was in his
office and I said why Freud
Tony why Freud why Freud
it was quite puzzled and he turned it
around variably on me and said well why
young and I was not prepared for that
question and so I sort of struggled
through it and what I came up with was
more than any of the other of the depth
psychologists and psychological
theorists of the period and the
psychodynamic sort of people young takes
seriously the realities of the soul and
by that I don't mean it nor did young
you know kind of like a disc Arnott you
know it's not a ghost living in your
body that's not what we're talking about
but rather that young takes seriously
and directly you know take sort of
reverentially the notion that spiritual
reality and a sort of dimension of
meaning right that is abstract and not
easily grounded in physical things is
not just relevant but central to sort of
human purpose and flourishing and so
because Jung took that so seriously but
also because I had you know the sort of
the naturalistic imperative at work you
know I had a lot of work ahead of me in
terms of trying to square those things
all together right yeah and figuring out
like what you know what what it means to
to have both of those commitments
and like I said that's far from I think
a fully solved problem but it's the you
know the time went on it's been almost a
decade and I had theory from from before
it's become increasingly clear to me
that actually these things play together
far better
then I think people might believe at
first glance mmm yeah that would you
well there's two things that I wanted to
give you a chance you were giving a very
balanced overview of young but you
recently told me that Young's reputation
has gone through a bit of redemption
maybe you could share that with people
yeah sometimes I feel like I was the
last person to know this so you know I
teach young here at the University I
have the great pleasure to teach the
interdisciplinary courses in Union
Theory suite at new college and you know
it as a young enthusiast right I'm often
called upon to defend young and the the
main thing that of course comes up
routinely is wasn't he a Nazi which you
know that's a pretty serious charge and
you know there is a kind of an obvious
split right in German intellectuals
right that this is the Tillich Heidegger
split Heidegger signs up to the party
Tillich says no and leaves and young
traditionally has fallen I think in
public perception to this funny middle
ground and I know some people that
really really believed he was like a
deep anti-semite and so on and so forth
now that had never really washed with me
it just didn't make sense it was clear
that a lot of the Freudians had accused
him of anti-semitism but they didn't
like him for a lot of reasons right
right and there was some fairly vicious
exchanges in the psychodynamic community
after the young Fred breakup but then I
found out like a little under a year ago
so young part of the problem was that
Young had stayed on in a kind of
official capacity somewhat answering so
when the Nazis took over young decided
to remain in charge of the you know like
of the psychoanalysis Society and
obviously Freud being Jewish that was
that was a no-go but young stayed on and
the idea was that like maybe he's sort
of profited from that etc etc and
there's some questions that he might
have been you know a sympathizer at the
very least like not sufficiently
resistant right but in fact I found out
recently that it's on record that young
in fact worked for the OSS ah so so the
OSS was though the world war ii
precursor to the CIA yeah so it was sort
of the intelligence you know the spy arm
basically of the Allied forces and Young
had an official an official designation
as
four eight eight he reported through
Allen Dulles as Secretary to Allen
Dulles who became the first director of
the CIA and was a quite significant
world war two agent and as it turns out
this stuff is all still classified which
itself is pretty weird but he did
psychological profiles of high-ranking
Nazi Party members like he interacted
with people and then I guess archetypal
II profiled they're like mythic
landscape or whatever and Allen Dulles
is on record as having said that you
know people will never really know how
much of a contribution Professor Jung
made to the winning of the war which is
yeah it's neat so yeah he wasn't he
wasn't a Nazi business spy that's cool
or something he was a secret agent yeah
yeah yesterday its native so it's good
to finally have an answer in that
respect but yeah so the reason I wanted
to talk to you in more depth as well as
you know I you know my work we do a lot
of work together and I've done this
series awakening for the meeting crisis
and I see young as a pivotal figure I
group him with a bunch of other people I
call the prophets of the meeting crisis
I'm using prophet in the Old Testament
sense not a fortune-teller but somebody
who's speaking truths that have a like
have a that are like revelation they
need to they're not being noticed
something needs to be seen something
needs to be understood mm-hmm and for me
you know books like modern man in search
of a soul and you mentioned the idea of
a soul seemed to me to be clear
documents portending and trying to craft
a response to the meeting crisis and so
I thought maybe we could talk a bit
about that and then in connection with
that I'm sure another person you
encountered at U of T especially with
your interest in young with jordan
peterson and you're teaching courses on
young so I imagine that comes up and I I
think one of the reasons that Jordans
work has well there's a couple of
reasons more so one of the reasons why
Jordans work is so has so much resonance
is so popular I guess that's the right
word especially amongst one group of
people the people that I'm in dialogue
with people like Jonathan pazzo and Paul
van der clay is that Jordan seem to have
crafted an interpretation of young
similar in some ways to Joseph Campbell
but and then he seemed to have used that
as a way of putting his finger on the
pulse of the meaning crisis so I thought
maybe we could talk about sort of those
two topics we could talk about your take
on young in the meaning crisis perhaps
your take on my take on young in the
meeting crisis and then how does Jordan
Peterson's work fit into this and what
do you think about that in general
because I'm sure you have to have
thoughts about this because you are
teaching these courses about young at
UofT
yeah so so yeah well you know looking at
sort of prophets of the men in crisis
generally speaking I thought you that
was interesting as I'm sort of watching
you build the diagram I was like oh wow
that's where this is going and it was
very it was it was very interesting sort
of account like you drew some lines that
were somewhat unexpected and I might
have in fact on some extra lines in
there maybe I will
in terms of Jung's role in that you know
I think you do identify some really
important threads right there the
influences that sort of go into young
that naturally form a part of the kind
of meaning crisis account right so Conte
is the ultra obvious choice right you
didn't mention Hegel but like a lot of
the approach to the Union synthesis of
the opposites is essentially pulls from
the you know Hegelian dialectic and the
practice of dialectic Plato is a very
obvious very blatantly obvious influence
on young young allegedly did not like
Kierkegaard which yeah which might be
interesting to touch on but yeah the the
big thrust I think you're right quite
right aside from his contemporaries is
is Conte and in fact so much so that
Jung Jung referred to contest his
philosopher he he was known in his
medical residency to sort of bitch that
he now only had time to read content
Sunday so you know there's no question
that you know concepts you know the the
notion that we have sort of categories
right the structure our experience
innately is very closely related to the
Union
of yeah get you can get that sort of by
taking the Young's notion of the
categories and Plato's notion of the
forms and sort of that's right mashing
them together mashing them yeah I mean
Young's concept of the archetype and
this is one of the problems when it
comes to studying young you know I often
field questions there like when when
young uses this term what does he mean
that's problematic it's a deeply
problematic because his work is
occurring over a 50-year span and what
he means changes hmm now for one thing I
think young as a thinker was less
concerned with consistency than
completeness to you know the good alien
idea so because of that you know there
is a grab-bag quality to his work you
know you'll be going along and you be
like yeah yeah sure okay grail meth good
you know parental issues whatever UFO is
fine right that kind of thing happens
fairly routinely where his desire to be
inclusive in the way that his
phenomenology functions means that
sometimes the pieces are a little loose
but above and beyond that his specific
ideas about what terms mean shifts
pretty considerably over the period so
just to take archetype as an example
let's talk a little bit about that sure
okay so what I mean I was improving I
was impressed by Storz idea that Young
has an organic model as opposed to
Freud's hydraulic model right and so I
thought it was appropriate I want to
hear your feedback on this too to see
young III get that it's anachronistic
but nevertheless maybe it's a way of
properly appropriating his work to see
young in terms of like dynamical systems
idea a self-organizing system and then
you have a tractor states within that
self-organizing system things like that
right and I was sort of pitching the
architects along that line so the model
I had in mind is like archetypes are
like settings of a parameter on a state
space as a dynamical and the dynamical
system moves through the state space and
it has attractors and those attractors
are sort of the image or the content of
the archetype but they're not the
archetype itself the archit right is is
that is that what would you think about
that well okay so the the very nature of
the archetype right off the bat and you
know call dr. Conte is that you know the
the thing in itself you can
get at yes oh the you know trying to
describe the archetypes and any final
sense is sort of doomed to failure
and young offers a variety of
explanations for that some of it is just
like it's inaccessible because it is
before the subjective and objective
world right so you know the archetype
exists sort of outside of the objective
and subjective it it's part of the unis
mundus and therefore you can't get at it
that's one possibility but another
possibility that he gives sometimes it's
like well it's just too big it's too big
for your ego to grapple it's like you
can't pull it in because there's there's
too much of it and it's kind of a
shapeshifter
like I said he moves around in this
stuff I think they attract in Traktor
state space and the idea of using
dynamical systems to talk of it as an
interesting lens like it's it's an
interesting and one that I share it
maybe sanitizes a particular aspect
though of Jung's focus on the psyche as
a living system
mm-hmm so obviously right like if you
treat organic living systems as
dynamical systems systems right yeah
it's a problem but there's something
about talking about it in terms of state
space and attractors that maybe doesn't
quite capture so the analogy that I use
sometimes okay is like in Freud's
hydraulic system you just have forces
right pushing each other around so if
something is in your unconscious if you
have a repressed content for instance
it's kind of like when you lose your
keys in the couch you go to check your
pocket and they aren't there and right
and where are your keys and the thing is
if you pull all the couch cushions out
eventually you will find the keys right
there they are they're not going
anywhere
or you might like your phone maybe or
appear at your phone might go off and
you'll be like oh it's in the couch and
nevertheless it's static it's sort of
there and in your complexes and things
don't have that form because they have
that living reality it's more like
trying to catch a mouse behind your
couch so if you hear a mouse behind your
couch and you pull the couch out the
mouse is gone right this is one of the
sort of justifications for why you
should do analysis in tandem with
somebody because they can wait at the
other end of the couch to catch it when
you pull the couch out so to speak
right so that idea right that it's a
dynamical system you know if you can
sort of extend that notion to really
include the idea of the living system
that's yeah adjusting it has its own
goals you certainly can
yeah but I think state space sometimes
throws people off from that that
dimension of it so like if the system is
is self-organizing and it has the
ability to sort of adapt to changing
circumstances kind of like what I talk
about when I talk about parasitic
processing things like that so I would
even go a little further I would say
that it sort of maybe even explicit in
yo but implicit in this particular take
on young it's not just that it's
adaptive and it's not just that it's
flexible and it's not even just that
it's self constituting it is intentional
it has its own ideas about things mm-hmm
and its own goals and so that's sort of
central in some sense to the
psychodynamic model right the
psychodynamic model at its heart right
which precedes Freud and Jung
considerably right like really the PERTs
based model goes back to the ancient
Greeks at some level earth but when we
consider it in terms of the unconscious
you know in the modern sense the the
psychodynamic model is a rejection of
the unitive bias we all have this unit
of bias that we are singular unitive
beings and that you know but in fact we
know from a raft of scientific evidence
and from you know loads of anecdotal
experience that people can share that in
fact what we are is a bunch of different
forces or beings in a dynamic
relationship to each other that all
happened to mostly answer to the same
name and live at the same address so
that really then I mean there's a sense
then that Freud's notion or notion of
the soul then is going to be sort of
deeply heretical right because then it's
not going to be the metaphysical locus
of one's personal identity of it the way
you're describing it you've got sort of
micro agencies at work so what that what
does the soul then become in that model
is certain I mean they're if there
so one way one deep and ancient way of
understanding the soul certainly and
long-standing tradition tradition is
when I say John when I'm deeply and most
directly and ultimately pointing to is
my soul that man
yeah well or my soul in the Christian
sense I think yeah that's that's that
it's all about me that I identify with
that is going to that is seeking
salvation and some kind of integrated
sure individual non divisible individual
non dividable right whereas that that if
what you're saying is the case then Jung
does not have that model at all no I
don't think he does
and and I think that a lot of this that
you know the term individuation really
screws with people ah
so share that please so individuation is
like you know some people tend to tag
this as sort of the Union enlightenment
and I'm not sure that that's quite
accurate but individuation is sort of
the it's hard to say when when Jung uses
it whether he means it to be descriptive
or prescriptive is it a goal that one
has or it's simply a description of what
the mind does but it's this like
movement towards being who you are okay
that's kind of the idea that you are
becoming more fully who you are over
time a lot of people take the term
individuation to indicate that they are
eventually going to become in divisible
yeah right that they'll become unitive
and Locke but I don't think that's
actually indicated at all and sort of in
looking at how that works and thinking
about it sort of in those terms it gets
closer to what you mean so okay so in
the Union system right you have sort of
you know multiple multiple sort of loci
of agency right so you have your
complexes right which are various forms
and then there are a few things like the
you know the whelmed of the ego the
shadow itself right the persona when
you're looking at the relationship
between ego and self particularly the
ego is the center of your conscious
experience and it's the center of your
self-identification and one way to look
at sort of the process of individuation
is that you know everything else that
happens is just facilitating a
particular change in the relationship
between the ego and the
yeah the download yeah one of the ways
that I think so one of the ways that I
think is useful to think about this or
the metaphor that I teach often is the
shift from the Giulia geocentric the
heliocentric thinking okay so imagine
for a second that the ego is the earth
okay so of course the earth thinks that
it's the center of the universe right
that's the geocentric model and it looks
into the sky and we see we see the
bodies in the heavens moving around
right the Sun rises and falls with a
certain degree of regularity the moon
goes through its phases whatever and we
see the planets moving in this frankly
kind of erratic way and as we try to
model that right we build worries and
systems of rotation and in order to make
the mathematics of this model the system
we have to add increasing like epicycles
right and elaborate this and what's the
big Copernican shift the big Copernican
shift and this was not a new idea to
Copernicus right goes back to the
pythagorean's and the church knew about
it yeah Aristarchus right you know the
big move is that you know we treat the
Sun as the center and of course
Copernicus himself is very guarded yeah
at that no way the Galileo isn't yeah so
we treat the Sun as the center and why
do we do that because it makes the math
easier
similarily right if you are standing on
ego and you look up and you think ego is
the center of the system then the
movements of the other bodies in the
system are highly erratic and difficult
to predict it makes no sense trying to
relate everything back to ego means that
things are confusing and weird right
mm-hmm
if instead you realize that the center
of the system right is that thing up
there right the self and the self and
the Sun you know Co appear in the
literature all the time right it's like
of course God is the Sun what else would
it be
so you know when when you suddenly treat
the self as the center of the system and
realize that everything including your
ego is actually existing in a systematic
relationship to that suddenly the
motions of your psyche becomes sort of
more explicable more predictive
when you realize that not everything
that's going on in your psyche is
serving you the ego right so what does
that what would that a couple questions
first of all the first question is what
does that look like phenomenologically
is it you know it sounds similar to me I
think people have pointed this out two
aspects of Vedanta well the relationship
between the ego and the Ottoman right
and but what does that look like and
maybe that's part of the confusion with
enlightenment because Ryan Vedanta
that's clearly an aspect of
enlightenment and then secondly the more
I see what you're saying and the more
we're drawing out these connections the
more tortured the relationship between
Jung and Christianity now seems to me
very much yeah
I mean young young is not a Christian
realms a Gnostic yeah well I mean you
know it the Christian Gnostics right and
and likewise you know you know there
were forms of Christianity that dipped
into that right like the Nestorians
right had that court of the Divine
double built into it yeah we can get to
that in a sec so what's the relationship
well I mean the thing is that well first
of all what does look like phenomenology
phenomenologically so and then there and
then that will explore the morals so
that tells you about the relationship I
mean you know the thing that said is and
there are sort of intermediary stages
right generally speaking within sort of
Union individuation you're not you're
not aiming to have a direct encounter
with the self right away right there so
typically speaking you're talking about
doing shadow work first that's called
the apprentice piece typically in the
literature then you're doing work with
the anima animus your contra sexual soul
image okay and then eventually that
segues through into the wider wooly
menagerie of archetypal forces and
beyond that the self soul or self also
reach as you're reaching towards the
self is it reaching towards you because
you describe these things as if they
have at least kind of a a para
intentionality or something like yeah so
so the the self often gets described as
the center and totality of the system
and that throws people the center and
totality but I think that if you
maintain the kind of solar system model
that makes no more sense right well
that's what I was trying to use the
attractor state right yeah yeah same
kind of thing so so if you think of the
Sun
you know it's like yes it's the center
and it's discrete but also it's cynical
anon you take the Sun out there is no
system everything flies off in a space
right so and it is sort of you know out
of an accretion disk or however much you
want to push on this cosmological
metaphor you know everything is sort of
around that what that looks like
phenomenology and phenomenologically so
this is a thing and this is where I
think Jung ends up with a really
interesting interesting and distinct
approach to much of the spiritual
material is that the encounter with the
self this central organizing meaning
producing right the thing that is
organizing all the other forces in the
psyche as often as not shows up in terms
of mystical and religious experience
that's the phenomenology of it mm-hmm so
sometimes I talk about depth psychology
and I sort of tongue-in-cheek like to
call it the theory and practice of
things you'll have to deal with anyway
right because many of the aspects of you
me and depth psychology specifically are
about having to take into account
aspects of your own psyche right that
you kind of can't get around and denying
them does you no good so Jung has that
position about about you know the divine
basically speaking - right he says at
the end of the day epistemologically
like what possible evidence could we get
in one direction or another that would
prove or disprove the existence of God
so this lines up with Hicks argument
about the spiritual ambiguity of the
empirical evidence that's right yeah
very much so I think you know in that
sense Jung is sort of an early important
non-theist
I've tried to argue that yeah I think
he's best understood as a non-theist
yeah I think so too although his work
gets cagey er towards the end I'm like
you know he moves like I said the
archetypes start being sort of the
psychic equivalent of like a reflex
right like getting your your knee tapped
and yeah right so they start like that
and I think that there's some good
material to think about them in those
terms which we can touch on but
eventually they become sort of cosmic
principles like as he moves to explain
them they become more and more like
content categories
right but like even more so more maybe
like the platonic well I was gonna say
it sounds like towards the end what
you're saying and guess I mean you've
read way more of young than I have but I
know there are several passages where he
explicitly excused metaphysics and
that's a Content thing but from what
you've been telling me and what we've
talked about this and past words the end
he starts talking metaphysically yeah
again and so it sounds like he maybe is
reversing the content isn't back towards
a more platonic model is that a fair
thing to say so actually I think that
what's happening is that in those late
stage passages he is attempting to
reconcile the trans jet
all finished the other thing first them
you know come back so so his take on God
is basically right it's that it's it's
that there is an absolute
epistemological limit you cannot get in
existence or non-existence of God
finally
but it's indisputable that people have
these forces and encounters in their
mind and his basic point is it's like it
doesn't matter at some level whether or
not there's actually a God because you
do have to have an encounter with the
part of yourself that is the meaning
forming and the locus of the sacred it's
sort of the inexhaustible wellspring of
your being you have to have some
encounter with that if you don't you end
up often kind of deeply stunted in terms
of your own potentials and and what
you're you know what your life is and
how you fit into it right and the thing
is the he points out is he's like and
this thing has certain ways of
communicating and the ways that it wants
to communicate or any symbolism in a
ritual so even though it may not be an
actual Divine Principle in some
alternate metaphysical sense you have to
deal with it like it is so that would be
an instance or where I talk about things
being psychologically indispensable but
not metaphysically necessary that's
right that's right okay so that's fair I
can understand that
so one criticism and I've heard it for
many people I think Durley makes a
criticism at one point I think uber is
making a criticism along these lines of
of young is this is all intrapsychic and
therefore it's missing
huge aspects existential mode aspects
that are central to the understanding of
God now that I'm I'm prompting you to
return back to there I think he wanted
to make about the trans dick tivity so
so I mean I understand that critique I
just don't think it's the case and you
know so please so the reason I don't
think it's the case is sort of a few
folds like one is you know we're used to
talking about the imaginal right and and
you know the deep dialogue between
Corbin and yes young at the the era
knows lectures which job can I just
interrupt would you say it's important
and I was trying to make a case that
it's it's important to the understanding
of young that the connection to Corbin
be made more explicit and more developed
scholastically yeah I mean as much as I
gripe about people deriving ideas from
young and not crediting him Young
himself was not always particularly good
about crediting sources of ideas right
you know he was a little bit self
mythologizing I think and consciously or
unconsciously hard to say but like you
know famously he essentially speaking he
and Freud stole work from sabina
spielrein yeah right she was the one who
had come up with the concept of like the
fana TOEIC death drive and she had a lot
of important contributions to early work
but no credit right so yeah I mean I see
I see Corbin nodding towards young yes
but I don't so much see young
referencing so yeah I I agree I think
that was an important relationship there
are no lectures generally speaking you
know as a set of sort of intellectual
encounters between people that were
doing that work in the period are
remarkable did that ever lend you my
copy of no you didn't but you should
it's really good anyway yeah so bringing
it back you're gonna go back into the
imaginal and and this this critique of
young as being merely intrapsychic right
so okay so when we talk about the
imaginal and we talk about it in terms
like active imagination right it's
relatively I think easy
so for people to pull into the idea that
what you're talking about is just a play
of imagination yeah but where that's
less clear is in the discussion of
dreams hmm
dreams as a form of the imaginal right
because they're not sort of deliberate
and occurring in an overlay on the
conscious mind are spontaneously
produced right spontaneously produced
imaginal material and so they sort of
more directly speak to this interface
point between the experiencing self
right and the sort of the self which
makes and when you look at that material
in the way that they talk about dream
interpretation in particular right like
marie-louise von Franz who was one of
Jung sort of foremost you know disciples
in to some extent popularizer right she
wrote very lucidly and she often said
about dreams that when you're dealing
with a dream simple you know somebody
appears in your dream your father
appears in your dream it's always
pointing outwards and inwards always
homeless and the thing in fact when you
do dream interpretation I noticed it
when I was in analysis and I noticed it
with my own clients is that more often
than not people have tendency to see
dream material as pointing outwards
right but not to pick up that it's
pointing inwards I see and Vaughn
friends actually I don't know how much
of this emphasis was Jung's himself but
von Franz actually sort of said like
really you should count that as 20%
outwards an 80% inwards I'm not so sure
about that I actually think that a lot
of young later work around the cycloid
right which was this term that he had
for something right that the archetype
simultaneously reached into the material
and the psychic worlds and he was
basically I think you know he's trying
to solve the mind-body problem at some
level right but he was doing it in this
funny roundabout way because he was in
dialogue with Wolfgang Pauli and they
thought maybe if they through quantum
mechanics at it they could crack it
right I think they just didn't have the
they didn't have the tools yeah but but
the transgender is is very much a
preoccupation for him and when you do
specifically dream analysis dream
interpretation that quality of pointing
outwards and pointing inwards is is
central holding both of those things in
mind simultaneously is central to
understanding what it is that's
happening in a dream
so could could could dream symbols and
perhaps archetypes in general therefore
afford something like sensibility
transcendence were you getting where
you're getting an insight that's both
directed outward and inward at the same
time like John Wright talks about yes
well but but I think it's hard for
people to do of course so yeah I mean
absolutely you know most people when
they have that dream symbol I mean you
know lots of people have had and we sort
of sort of smirk right it's like you're
somebody you know you know your partner
or something has a dream and they're
like halt just had a dream and you just
did something terrible and they're kind
of mad at you and you're like about that
okay but so you know that outward facing
aspect of dreams and then people will
tend to sort of hand wave it but people
don't naturally speaking tend to
gravitate towards what dreams are saying
about themselves right the dreams are
less messages than they are sort of an
immersion in the process of your psyche
a participatory knowing a participatory
knowing right I mean you know it's hard
to grasp I do this stuff pretty much
full-time and have done for a long time
but when I really sit with the idea it's
like so I have a dream and in that dream
I'm talking to you know my friend you
know and but who am i interacting with
I'm not interacting with him so Who am I
interacting with I'm interacting with
myself like some portion of my mind and
yet I'm not consciously doing this but
some part of me is and of course we are
now used to in neuroscience and
cognitive science the idea that we are
sort of conjuring the hallucination of
the world around a set of scant data
right but it's very clear in a dream
especially like a lucid dream where
those interactions can be quite rich and
they can be quite have a lot of
phenomenological detail and depth the
add one not last night but the night
before really yeah it's been a while I
had one like a month ago mmm I keep
meaning to get back into it but that's I
have to do that in January so so I want
to slow down here a little bit I'm
twenty that's really interesting so just
because like the Buber critique
because you know you're not picking up
on the existential modes and you know
and Bluebird has something you know the
I thou are yet which is I argue is very
analogous to froms
having mode and behavior and these are
existential modes and they're inherently
transductive yeah they're they they're
both processes by which you're assuming
identities participatory knowing yeah
and I assigned identities and there's a
conformity relationship between them
they're their code determining code
defining yeah and so I get this sense
and I and I see just to bring back
really we're on false I see alchemy as
one describes it as inherently
transductive because you're you're doing
this transformation of the psyche and
you're trying to get it to conform with
the material world and you're trying to
get the two to get some sort of mutually
afforded disclosure happening is that a
fair interpretation yeah partly but
partly it's also about using projection
right right as an innate capacity to
externalize the contents of your psyche
to a place where you can work on them
without it being so personal right so
it's it's doing it's doing it's doing
too thick right so what I'm trying to
get at the Philosopher's Stone is both
an overcoming of deep patterns of
self-deception with the projection yeah
but it isn't it also given me some
access I don't mean scientifically but
right some access to you know patterns
in reality that will help me it make
more better sense of the world yes so so
to bring this back around to the
geocentric heliocentric right okay good
when you have that sort of mystical
divine encounter or such as it is with
the self right one of the things you
point out is that that experience the
encounter with the self is always deeply
humiliating mm-hmm he's quite kind of
keen on this it is always humiliating no
did he mean that because I've made a
distinction in the series there's two
ways there's our modern meaning where
humiliation is a pejorative thing it's a
bad thing right and then there's
humiliation in the original sense which
is the engendering the creation of the
futility of humility I think it's both
it's both I think it's both so I think
when he means that what he means is that
it's a soul shattering experience I mean
realizing that you are not the center of
your own universe yeah that it's not all
about you
I mean that's fundamentally that is the
heart of the encounter between the ego
and the self it's not all about you
you you have a role to play and the ego
has a role to play the conscious mind
has a role to play but you are not the
only game in town and you're not calling
the shots what I'm trying to get at ya
is but it produces that humility also
right no no and I get that and I can see
why that would be if you'll allow me
epistemic lien existentially valuable
yeah what I'm trying to get like this is
the questions getting clear in my mind
what's the relationship between gaining
that humility towards the self
you're not the whole psychic show and
gaining that humility towards reality so
what's the relationship because there's
a clear relationship in vedanta trim
between rahman is brahman right right
there's a becoming more I don't want to
use the word all use Ottman because
self-centered sounds ridiculous wrong
area so what's the relationship become
between becoming Hockman centered rather
than egocentric and becoming Anto
centric rather than egocentric because
in vedanta they're clearly allied as
being mutually reinforcing
interpenetrating is that a fair thing to
also see and young or am i imposing on
you no I think that's fair so but but so
there isn't a logical identity no it's a
non logical it's a non logical identity
right it's it's kind of yeah but but
it's maybe yeah non-duality is closer
because it's not it's not the case that
sort of self and ego are the same right
but nor is it the case that yeah in some
ways they they in some ways they are I
mean right because ego is part of self
and yet distinct from right so there
there is in the work of individuation a
kind of simultaneous differentiation and
integration a complexification
complexification and this is a thing
generally when we're talking about
individuation you're talking about
having an encounter that puts you into a
state of metaphysical and
epistemological humility relative to
your own psyche and the forces inside of
it and the idea is that you want to
develop different relationships with
these parts of yourself you want to get
things moving in a systems that you can
understand who and what you are
without having to center everything on
your ego need right but that means
developing both a sense of identity with
the system but not direct identity if
you develop direct identity with the
self in the union system that's bad no
it's inflation so I get that so sir I'm
not trying to trivialize that yeah no I
just said it's important so I get that
you want the non do all right identity
that's why I think the term
participation is a good term between the
ego and itself what I'm trying to get at
is in so again back to the the Bluebird
critique the existential mode right
there's also relation what's the
relationship between the self and
reality and and this is where the
content aspect always sort of trips me
up when I try to get too young and
that's why that's what I was saying
weathers a simile in Vedanta it's like
yes the ego must realize its non-dual at
one mint with Artman but then once it
does that that affords it in a
participatory knowing the realization
that Atman is Brahman which is the
ground of the psyche and the ground of
the and the ground of being right have a
deeper and this this was boobers concern
because Bluebird is concerned he saw God
is the ground of being and he thought
that Jung was reducing God to the ground
of the psyche so it sort of depends
where you want to make your chalk mark
on the 50-year line ah please so so the
the further along you go it seems to me
I think you'll always had sympathies
towards this idea but he somewhat to
manage the perception of him as a kooky
mystic and somewhat because he himself
wanted to rein in his tendencies towards
inflation right he starts out with a
relatively grounded sort of biologically
metaphorically driven idea of what all
this stuff is so you know when when
we're giving this opening idea that like
you know your your psychological
encounters effectively structure your
reality and so you have to deal with it
anyway sure right and and it's as close
as it comes in some ways right even if
you take a completely grounded this is
all just happening in your mind it's
still happening in your mind and
completely changing your mind and what
salient to you and what stands out to
you and your experience of wonder in it
I mean
important it's huge right over but it
could all be contained within your head
right in the early part of young as that
goes on he's trying to square it more
and more and some of this I mean gets
into some of the you know for some
people zany or aspects of his work if
we're talking about something like
synchronicity hmm we are breaking
straight out of yeah right so so
synchronicity I mean lots of people are
familiar with this term but
synchronicity is the idea of meaningful
coincidence and you'll had a
long-standing interest in sort of
parapsychological material right but
also in these seemingly meaningful
coincidences that he felt were not
adequately explained by standard
rational sort of you know letting the
air out of his version of the miraculous
yeah very much and as he you know went
deeper and deeper on attempting to
understand synchronicity which he felt
was a real thing that needed to be
grappled with and he has some
predecessors he was he was somewhat
familiar with the work of a camera who
had like the law of sea reality other
people have been interested in sort of
coincidences as a thing that may
actually be not coincidental right right
so as he goes deeper down the rabbit
hole in terms of synchronicity in terms
of seemingly external manifestations of
psycho events so he gets interested in
UFOs and he starts to look at like UFO
sightings and stuff as being but also
you know the appearances of the Virgin
Mary in the sky this kind of thing as
being well what is that right what's
happening because that doesn't seem to
be strictly subjective it seems that
it's very least its interest objective
or something what a whole group of
people see that and then he's
increasingly interested in the idea that
if indeed it is the case that his notion
of of this stuff sort of bridges the
mind-body gap that it may stand outside
of that altogether and at that point
what we're dealing with the supernatural
entities that's and so that's the that's
the difference you start to get towards
the end of yo and he's sort of I think
he's just caved in Niccolo after his
heart attack you know he has a heart
attack near-fatal heart attack and after
that I think he's a full on he's a full
on mystic he believes that the things
that he's talking about are part of the
fundamental structure of the universe
that to me you know I I'm an aggressive
militant agnostic but most things you
know so I believe in taking on a really
strong degree of epistemological
humility I think that it's important to
hold metaphysics lightly because we
don't know like we can have some degrees
of plausibility and whatever but like
our both our cultural and personal
emphasis on certainty this is something
I might come back to if we're talking
about this it's it's sort of out of
control and in as tendency like we have
a tendency to shut off lines of
possibility so I keep a pretty broad you
know state of mind but a lot of the time
that stuff is pretty gone so even for me
like my tendency is feel like is it
really the case that the gesture is a
fundamental structure of reality like
maybe maybe that's the case but but it
seems to me that probably there might be
sort of easier to get to explanations
that are a little bit more
naturalistically grounded but don't rob
any of that of any of its like wonder or
impact ok well that's that's that's
that's a great segue I mean first of all
though I you know that I've trying to
develop especially with Leo work on
plausibility and it's playing a central
role and that that's actually much more
important than the rather quixotic
pursuit as you said of certainty and it
also tends to link knowledge are more
clearly to wisdom whereas the pursuit of
certainty keeps it keeps knowledge and
wisdom separate from each other
because wisdom is often defined as well
how you behave in certain situations of
significant uncertainty and things like
that right so I'm invited greement with
that I but the segue that came to mind
well there's there's some threads I want
to keep Saul just announce them I want
to come back because now the recollected
that the Youngs non-theism and the
relationship to Christianity is now
giving even more tortured in my mind
yeah around this and and that eventually
i think has to bring us back to talking
about Jordan's work sure but
perhaps before I give you a chance to
address that I'd like to know what you
think about you know well the attempts I
make for example when you talk about
aspects of the psyche that are deeper
than the ego try know I talk about the
priya going nature of relevance
realization and how it's this recursive
and um you know massively
self-organizing thing and how it can
beset us was something that looked like
dynamic versions of Jungian complexes
parasitic processing so like what do you
see there and because I take it that
that's been part of your project right
and so obviously for egocentric reasons
I'm interested in the reference also for
scientific reasons I'm interested in it
what do you see about the relationship
between young and relevance realization
to put it broadly ok so I can maybe sort
of work backwards so you know you were
talking about young to some extent and
the relationship between young and
Corbin and the divine double yeah and
the idea of having sort of a trans gel
right that's all in episode 48 yeah yeah
because it's a I'm influenced by Stan's
idea that it's a it's I hesitate I don't
want to use the word archetypal but it's
this it's a it's it's it's an it's a
transgenic keeps showing up right that's
the whole point of the book and then I
said you it's clear is ice white clear
it's clear and Corben's
attend deniable in Corbin and it's I
think it's very clear until ik you know
with the relationship as he puts it
between the existential in the essential
self you know it's all through
narcissism staying makes a very clear
case it's it's present in early forms of
Christianity Gnosticism it's rife and
then because of narcissism that led me
to say well maybe plausibly it's also in
Jung right I think it is I mean you know
the the notion of divine doubling and a
certain amount of like the assumption of
the archetype moving moving into the
archetype is sort of relatively central
to the the on-the-ground practice of
depth psychology and what do you mean by
that moving into the archetype so so
there is a kind of like
okay I'll give it I'll give you an
example so so when you'll we you know
the idea of the persona right you have
the ego the ego is your conscious mind
in some sense and it's it's everything
you seem to yourself separate from that
is the interface that you have with the
social world right and so the persona
derived from the theatrical mask right
and and it's an interface insofar as it
really is bi-directional you both put
things through it in a sense right it
reveals then it can also filters but it
also filters so so it contains your
social rule right you have to put on
certain types of masks to do certain
kinds of things and you we take this as
a given
generally speaking right like you know
if you're a lawyer and you've got court
you have to have certain kinds of
personality television law
notwithstanding you have to have certain
kinds of persona in order to do it same
thing goes for the Academy yeah being a
professor totally or being a student
right by the time students get into
undergrad none of them are standing on
their desk and screaming yeah or if they
are it's a highly anomalous event I hate
their so you know the ability to conform
to the expectations and social rules and
stuff is part of fitting in its both
right but also we push our individuality
out so it's a bit like if you're you
know sartorius artists current
Carlisle's book so it's a Bono Carla
yeah yeah but about the philosophy of
clothes right it's very funny right look
but one of the things that you get into
this with persona is you know clothing
reveals and it conceals right has that
that dual high daguerreian kind of
quality to it reveals and conceals we
say things about ourselves but we also
hide ourselves right okay so so if we're
sort of looking at that right we can we
can I'm wondering if that's actually the
best example now that I started to get
into it moving into the archetype yeah
I'm wondering if I should be moving into
the archetype or not I want take a break
here no I'm just thinking about it for a
second because if I start moving into
persona specifically no I'm gonna run
into having to unpack all of that stuff
I think maybe in fact I should move back
to talking about the divine double and
cell
okay instead okay okay so that's what I
will do instead okay so there's a
specific thing that you sort of unpack
around around that right which is this
idea that the divine double is standing
in aspirationally yeah I was trying to
get I was trying to link you and his
idea to calories idea of aspiration
because because it does it does a lot of
work because Callard has a very powerful
argument that this aspiration has to be
part of what we mean by rationality yet
she indicates but does not develop a
psychology around it that it has to have
this symbolic thing it had mentioning
the persona was actually helpful even
though you're not gonna go in it because
when you're aspiring you need something
that a Janus face like that it has to
that's right it has to draw you within
the frame that you're in and the person
that you are but it also has to be
beyond yes right and normatively
challenging you to become the person you
you're aspiring to be okay so we'll
leave it all my stumbly processing
that's that's the process of uncertainty
that's good okay so that's exactly what
I was getting at is that when we move
into persona we start out by faking it
until we make it we dawn it but persona
can become too tight it starts out
typically being aspirational so this
like the classic thing right early
undergrad you know philosophy papers
used to get slammed for using jargon and
sort of awkward right they're awkward
but the idea is they're trying on the
form and of course it's awkward because
they're imperfectly emulating and if
they could perfectly emulate it they'd
already be doing it right right they'd
already know what they were doing right
first we do it clumsily that serious
play that I've been talking exactly
exactly okay so the persona is sort of
an interface point for that but it can
come to fit too tightly there is
correspondingly a kind of inner right so
the corresponding point to the to the
persona which interfaces us with the
world of the social world specifically
the anima or animus right the oh so it's
the internal interface that's right okay
yeah which is why so you know he's never
knew that about the anima I didn't quite
understand it that way that's very
helpful yeah so the it's hard to
understand but that's why it's the soul
and it's distinct from the self this is
one of the things that I wanted to point
out with your divine double thing Isis
so it has a psychopomp ik function when
you start interfacing with it is so the
anima
is the soul it's the interface between
the ego and the cell that's right and
it's it is the psychopomp yes a
psychopomp is something that leads you
into right into the afterlife or the
underworld or between worlds or what
have you
yes so so the Contra sexual soul image
which I just force Orton to soul right
right is that is to the inner world what
the persona is to the outer world oh so
that means they must have a strange
relationship to well they have a
compensatory relationship and so where
the ego and the shadow for instance are
compensatory to some extent right they
that it's an either/or proposition
what's in each to some extent that turns
up in persona and soul and that's one of
the ways that that I and I think a fair
number of other sort of neo unions try
to look at this so that we don't get
into so much gender essentialism right
around like the inner woman and the
inner man and like that stuff gets
confusing given you know sort of more
modern thinking on this right sure but
if instead it's the case that all of
your externally focused you know
masculine traits your ideas about what
it is to be you know like I'm a man and
this is how I present myself and
whatever the corresponding traits drift
inwards and they become part of your
inner relatedness and because there
tends to be sort of us you know
statistical cultural clustering around
this stuff right
whether or not it's sort of gender
essential in the genetic sense it is in
a cultural sense and so you'll tend to
get right those traits accumulating okay
that figure that sort of soul figure
yeah I think is closer to what you mean
by the divine double-double and I mean
there are a few doubles there are
doubles and doubles and twins that's as
young as full of that kind of stuff so
the shadow has that quality too so what
you're saying is I was being I agree
with you now I think your critique is
excellent because in fact the what
you've just done Maps better on to the
original use so the divine double isn't
ultimately the God beyond all possible
gods the divine double is the psychopomp
ik figure it is nevertheless but you do
have a non logical identity with yes and
so did Stan's point is that your
individual not an individual right your
individual and that the relationship
with the divine double actually it
draws you beyond now the thing is so I
can I think you're right and I think I
see and there are other versions of this
right and we're curious young talks at
great length about more curious and more
curious is a kind of version of this
divine double that's even closer to the
center of being it partakes in all of
the paradoxical yeah sort of this it'll
hermaphroditic and you see you see that
in the Gnostics - right as you get as
you move I want to say higher but
there's all metaphors yeah this is it's
through the divine double so that's
that's important because that do that to
me then does strike me as perhaps maybe
I got to go back and see what how Dooley
is playing with these two that seems
like there's although that I think
they're both invoking the divine double
your on this divine double is more
closely Gnostic than telexes that's
right now I mean till it clearly has
narcissism in and he talks about the God
beyond the god of theism and all of that
but the the divine double is so I feel
like Tillich draws on the Gnostics in
order to I mean you know the the mid
twentieth century is like the high-water
mark for theology as the locus where we
were going to perform some kind of
cultural Redemption yeah and I don't
think we're there anymore
I mean now countless Catholics including
some friends of mine will disagree with
me but it seems to me like that's not
really where this is going to happen
we're not going to get a modern
theologian doing this so but Tillich
clearly falls into that arc yeah and it
seems to me that he draws on the
Gnostics he's pulling things from them
in order to run his project but you know
one was just a Gnostic yeah he's just a
Gnostic young got you know to an
important extent hammered with an
experience which he then attempted to
sort out so so we let's remember I want
you to eventually get back to how does
this bridge between young and relevance
realization so but also I just want to
put another pin given what you just said
and I mean IIIi was a little bit bold
but now you made me feel more confident
in the boldness I I said the formula for
young is cop is caught plus nost x
equals young with a sprinkling of
Schopenhauer things like a sprinkling of
power
so for her fair enough but given what
you just said and then given of course
the very tortured relationship between
narcissism into stanity this again makes
the relationship between young and
Christianity even more fraught sure I
mean look at its most basic right you
has a lot of interest in respect in
Christian symbolism right but as part of
a broader subset he doesn't identify
Christian symbolism as being sort of
unique unto itself right he sees it as
part of a broader set of rebirth and
resurrection and right this is your
point about him ultimately being a
non-theist yeah that's right and but
also that he you know he sees it as part
of a tradition so it's sort of the the
flowering within our age of that
tradition right the fish and so on and
so forth but really has lots of
parallels and precedents right but so
this is this overlaps sorry for interest
because surely who you know hmm I mean
he uses young as a basis for making a
critique of Christianity right well so
so you does clearly have okay I can give
you one example
you'll rejects out of hand the concept
of privacy Oh bony right right throws it
right out so right this is this is the
Augustinian idea please go ahead story
yeah so it's Augustine's idea that the
way to understand evil is not as having
any metaphysical substance in and of
itself rather it is merely the absence
of good right provision above me and so
the idea is there's just God and then
there are places that God you know I
don't know it's not shining as brightly
yes yeah it's the idea and young throws
that out he is right off the bat like a
duelist in this sense he says no no like
you have to treat these things as having
their own solidity and force and motion
and purpose no the devil needs his due
yeah you've made this point at the very
beginning right so I mean that's very
central to Jungian thinking and
something will actually come back to if
we talk about sort of the shadow yeah
and the way that the shadow works in
this sense so you know yeah you know
immediately and and he has some other
fairly deep critiques if you read his
it's a thin little book and it's a
strange book it's interesting but it's
strange right the answer to Joe yeah of
course right the answer to job is in
many ways
attempt to synthesize together the
meaning of Christianity together with
sort of our current you know age and and
what that means and one of the things
that you get in the deep young is the
idea that the archetypes sort of aren't
exactly totally outside of time and
space because they evolved culturally
mhm and so you know where we might talk
about like the axial age or something
Young tags of stuff you know with sort
of these two thousand year or you know
procession of the right whatever this is
called the cosmic seasons right no
cosmic months or something something
like that whatever it's astrology right
so so he identifies he's like two
thousand year long cycles and one of the
things that he says in the answer to job
so right story of job you know did you
do job in the series no I didn't okay so
a story of job right it's it's a late
Old Testament story and what you have is
God and the devil are sitting around on
a mountainside this is before they were
like I don't see what did I say the
devil oh yeah okay saving you right it
was still the job description yeah so
God and the adversary the angel that
does the adversarial stuff are sitting
on the side of a mountain and basically
they get into an argument about whether
or not if sufficiently bad things happen
to job God's faithful servant job will
denounce him and they take bats you know
Satan is like I bet you I can make his
day sufficiently terrible right this is
just like the bet in the dark night
right one bit one bad day we're all one
bad day so so they make this pact and
gods like your on and then with sort of
gods
go ahead he destroys jobs life give some
disease kills his children ruins his
fortune and you know the the original
text uses this as an opportunity to
really plumb some of our deepest sort of
questions and concerns and anxieties
around why do bad things happen to the
people is the problem that's the problem
of suffering and evil totally promise
suffering and evil and then there's this
final scene towards the end where
there's no answer but God appears out of
the world God so so job is sitting
around and talking to his buddies and
he's starting to get a little bit you
know like right and then God suddenly
appears from the whirlwind
and God delivers this speech which is
very interesting it's like he basically
questions job's knowledge he says you
have no idea what you're talking about
you know canst thou draw Leviathan up
with hook he brags about creating these
giant monsters and being able to defeat
them and being able to defeat them did
spout lay the foundations of the earth
basically God is like you you you
don't know if I could say that uh you
know like you you just have no idea what
you're talking about you're ignorant
worm I'm the creator of the universe but
okay III don't want to take too much
team out of I mean some people have
interpreted that is that what God's
doing is inducing a numinous experience
and then and part of the response yes to
the problem of evil is not a any kind of
philosophical proposition or argument
but it's like look here's the numinous
and you go it's like in like that it's
like that scene in Joe versus the
volcano you know Oh God whose name I do
not know thank you for my life because
he sees the madness right and it doesn't
it doesn't answer the fact that he
believes he has some kind of brain
cancer it doesn't resolve any of his
problems but he becomes grateful for his
life
because of the encounter with the
numinous and that's the answer right
beaut beautiful and terrible like the
see all who look on me she'll love me
and despair yeah yeah so for sure it I
think that's one aspect but the thing
that young tags on specifically okay is
this particular exchange because what
you'll reads into this is this kind of
encounter where it's like Joe basically
did nothing to deserve this yes and
after the encounter where job does kind
of knuckle under God feels remorse we
have a kind of an Old Testament figure
cuz you know Old Testament God is a
funny capricious figure right Regenesis
in us the Gnostics made a big deal
exactly and so this is a very gnostic
interpretation we have sort of old
nobodaddy right right who's throwing his
weight around in the bible you think I'm
just a he'll dodge snakes for you yeah
right we have this Old Testament Cod
that's hard to deal with hard to
reconcile right hard to chew through and
this was part of the Gnostic problem and
in the book of Job Young sees a moment
where that God feels remorse and that
for him is the moment where it's
necessary to then incarnate in the flesh
so that you can suffer he
see status to transmission book into
Christianity right that's just heresy
yeah totally that is not a conventional
Orthodox Christian idea in any way so
the ideal Italy Gnostic though very
deeply Gnostic so ya know I think young
is you know whether or not he would have
had the courage all along to say that he
was a gnostic because he was already
four plastered with a lot of labels as a
weirdo yeah yeah whether or not he would
have had the courage I mean one of his
earliest works around the period of the
red book is the seventh sermons yeah I
tried to I try to read them some of that
is very hard well it you know we had
reads like in Gnostic texts and trying
to read the Gnostic Gospels is it very
tough that for the gospel of truth or
the gospel of thomas gospel okay the
Gospel of Thomas is pretty good because
it just puts like a clarifying spin on
the synoptic Gospels it's like nice
little aphorisms that's good but like
you know perfect thunder mind
thunder perfect thunder perfect mind
yeah or you know a bunch of those other
ones where it's like constantly
unfolding Palomas and multi crown
monster its visionary right and of
course there are I think important
imaginal things happening yeah like the
chronics idea that you got you're
getting you're getting a different
interpretation of the sacred not as
something that should be fixed right but
is something that should become constant
ly transgressed that's right which gets
us back to the symbols yes right yeah
well so the inexhaustibility and the
trans Jack TIFF Nessa
yeah when I read seven sermons of the
Dead that young book I own it and I've
read it a bunch what I see there is not
something that's easy for me to directly
connect to but I can empathize with
because I've had comparable experiences
of poetry I've had I've had write
automatic writing poetry things that
that came through me or that was the
felt sense right of course at some level
I'm sure that biologically I produced it
but that was not the felt sense the felt
sense was that it was a thing that
happened to and through me yeah and that
contained sort of massive right
archetypal structure to it yeah there's
a distinction that Tanabe talks about
about self power and other power that's
crucial to certain aspects of Buddhism
and right effort is about getting the
balance between self power and other
power right
so I mean you invoked transductive 'ti
you invoked you know inexhaustibility to
invoke salience so try to bring it back
to again right like you okay so I'll
give them loking maybe I'll give you the
simple simple so this is how I think
about it I wouldn't want to put words in
young's mouth necessarily but this is
how i think about it i think about so
you know you talked I think in episode
32 your series about Montague and mutual
modeling okay and I often think about it
in those terms and in type what we're
talking about when we talk about
typology but in the simplest sense I
think about it in this way there are a
series of encounters that I can have
within my own mind okay with figures
that compose my psyche but are not
identical with the person I would call
Anderson but they're important parts of
my functioning those include things like
the internal neutral models I developed
for my parents right right right
who you know and this is the point that
I sometimes make it's like well that's
an area where Freud was right right
theory of mind we know that we have
theory of mind for other people before
we have it for ourselves yes and under
mutual modeling we know that
evolutionarily speaking it's absolutely
crucial that you be able to internalize
your parents yep often in fact your
enormous frustration as a young adult
you get a lot of your metacognitive
abilities through the Gonski and what
what you put those two things together
and what that means is your parents have
been living in your head longer than you
have
yes oh that's a good way of putting it
that's very provocative right I mean
that and in that sense like for an
impact attachment right or oh man I came
to that's Jeff McDonald's work and other
people's were totally right so so you
know you get that you get general
general kind of concepts of type and to
talk about type people get very you know
worked up about it but really type is
just category you know and category is
essential to doing any kind of abstract
thinking manipulating things in classes
that's type you know the fact that I'm
not interacting with every cat as a
radical individual but I have some basic
idea of where a cat wants to be
scratched and not be scratched
I might sometimes get surprised right
but for the most part right I form type
likewise we interact with type on a day
to day basis all the time and recognize
in other people even when we don't on
ourselves right when we say somebody has
a romantic type
and that's recently been put on
empirical footing people really do ya
have a romantic type right and to say
that romantic type is intertwined with
people's pathologies of attachment and
romance would be understating it even
right okay interject you just rocked an
insight into sure okay so if we have
sort of categorical relationships is
part of young getting us to not make a
modal confusion and shift from a
category and I get with our inner life
to an eye though yes ah ah yes that's
why it's about developing relationships
ah right so you come to a relationship
and this is why often I think people you
know the archetypes aren't things we
have exactly no no no they're there and
sort of they're somewhat fundamental
structures but the but the the fundament
of the structure is that they will form
not the specific contents and we have to
encounter those specific contents in
order to know ourselves and those
specific contents are best encountered
as people sort of yeah not quite but
sort of yeah those but not necessarily
right no I don't know I'm on the fence
personally about whether these aspects
of our mind possess that possess their
own subjectivity intrinsically or
whether it's the case that through the
practices that we engage in we allow
them to draw on the machinery of
subjectivity whether we person them
right we sort of allow them to exact
that machinery so we enter into a more
direct therapeutic relations right
exactly right
like so I'm on the fence I sort of
suspect just because of well with ideas
we've talked about around consciousness
and the structure of the brain and how
those things are related I don't see any
reason why the brain not only shouldn't
be able to but almost certainly
undoubtedly is supporting multiple
consciousness is evidence from lucid
dreaming and yeah there's evidence from
lucid dreaming I mean it goes right back
to split brain we've sort of known this
for a long time but we don't want to
support them more than one yeah and you
know unless you think that there's some
magic number of brain cells that kicks
off consciousness it's like I don't see
any reason why certain
of structures and functional patterns
can't have separate operating
consciousnesses and when you look at
structural dissociation as a field it
just becomes increasingly obvious like
this is happening right and res lab
right hypnosis dissociation we can get
into that but the point is I don't know
per se whether or not there are already
multiple people running around your head
or there are multiple dynamics and
forces and the best way for you to deal
with them is to interact with them and
turn them into people the spirit of
finesse yes spirit of finesse but also
like the kind of projective love that
you use with children and the projective
love God uses to turn us into people
agape I like that kind of connection I'm
sort of seeing yeah so I'm just trying
to bring it one more time around to the
connection I keep interrupting you too
let's talk a connection between young
and the way you are connecting young and
relevance realization like you just did
it again yeah yeah well you know we're
circumambulating yeah that's a bore of
the term yes oh by the way it comes
originally from Plato right so so you
know there's this variety of encounters
but like I said I think that you know
when we're talking about the divine
double for instance okay that is an
aspect of encounter that you would have
with yourself with the shadow with
mercurius with whatever but then I think
that there is a level below or beyond
that which is a kind of direct
transgenic 'el identity relationship
with the machinery of your own cognition
right so the pre ago ik pre-conceptual
relevance realizes relevance right and
maybe something beyond that - I don't
know yeah I like I'm not totally sure
how deep that can go but at the very
least relevance realization and I think
that's actually probably it the best to
take that I have on what it is to
encounter the cell mmm the self isn't
any of these individual features it's
the thing that allows these individual
features to come into existence and
supports them to begin one right right I
see that that's that's what very clearly
put and God wears many masks you you
know so to directly encounter it is
nearly impossible you encounter it
through its manifestations it's a shape
changer the closer you get to it the
more obvious that becomes and that's
Mercurius is intrinsically sort of
paradoxical and shape-changing and a
trickster and is the son of God in the
devil as they say and has all these
other things right it's sort of
approaches non-duality zhe's something
that is beyond duality right and it's
sort of hovers on the very threshold of
entering into that Yunis mundus state
which is the you know that the the ERG
runned the thing that makes it all right
and in the sent the center of our own
being as as the beings that we are
attempting to figure out and you know
how to carry on sense right that I think
is probably the best that's my best shot
anyway no that's that's very helpful
that's very clear so as you know I've
tried to use the relevance realization
machinery and I guess at times a
complicated way but at least a complex
way of trying to get a grip on the
meaning crisis yeah well funny actually
I was thinking about this in the way in
and I was thinking about the meaning
crisis relative to young and the way
that spiritual crisis in young is the
entry point and I thought oh if I can
borrow the meaning crisis and blow
something from The Simpsons in the Union
sense we're actually facing the meaning
Christ eternity it's the meaning Christ
eternity yes everything is falling apart
and terrible and on fire and this is
that's the door right that's interesting
so the reason I brought that up is
because I think Young is a prophet of
the mean crisis and we talked about you
know part of what part of how I see him
a prophet is precisely his critique of
the the established religion it's not
doing a good enough job and that's
that's that's that's I think a fair
that's a pervasive theme that's true
young I think and that then lines up
with like I said his relationship to
religion and Christianity particulars a
much more distanced relationship so why
I'm bringing that up is that that brings
us up to the topic of the meaning crisis
young and then of course
Jordan Peterson and his take on that
and the reading of the Bible that he's
done and like so it's clear to me that
that Jordan has said many insightful
things I don't want to detract from that
but it's clear to me that one of the
things he's doing and and in this sense
he echoes Joseph Campbell Joseph
Campbell sort of was a big star for a
while when I was growing up trim right
but he has the influence over of the
original stars we watched him with bill
moyers on it's on Netflix the power of
myth and not in the huge influence on
the the original for the original three
movies yes star wars and because exactly
that he brings up young as a way of
giving people access to symbolism and
self transcendence and self
transformation in response to the
meeting crisis and I see part of why
Jordan skyrocketed part of it of course
was a whole political thing that I don't
want to get into but part of it is he
does something similar to Campbell but
he does it I'm much more charismatic Lee
yeah I think and he also has he has so
much more powerful medium at his
disposal which is social media YouTube
acceptor and so in and and this is not
I'm not gonna engage in any left-handed
criticisms of Jordan does not be
dismissive but I think that's part of
the power of of his why he he was taken
up by so many people is precisely the
power that that is in young yet has a
response to the meeting crisis yeah
Jordan Jordan has his hand in contact
with a current of mythic right and you
know the yeah that's powerful stuff and
it can talk about that by way of Star
Wars because I think actually that's a
really interesting for example you know
as far as the meaning crisis goes yet
young you know young wrote a really
interesting essay during the rise of
Nazism or immediately before called
Wotan which I think is not as widely
read as it should be where he's talking
about sort of this this rise of a
particular figure within the Germanic
psyche and what this is going to mean
and but at the same time he spends lots
of time talking about how modernity is
breaking down these old structures he's
a student of nature it's not like
unaware that God is dead and we have
killed him and how can we get the blood
off our hands on what
we need to become to justify our crime
he knows all that and in fact in ion
which is perhaps his most profoundly
weird book and I say that you know like
pointedly uh you know ion is the second
part of collected works volume 9 the
first part is it's relatively
straightforward and it has to do with
sort of different archetypal structures
and complexes but the second part ion is
this really interesting wide-ranging
book that's hard and one of the things
that he says an ion he gets into this
like you know cycles of history thing
and he says you know the faintest
rudiments were on 2,000 year cyclists so
the famous or thereabouts so the
faintest rudiments of the future society
are actually visible now he said and I
think that will transition to that
Society in about five or six hundred
years
I remember reading that and thinking oh
right like this isn't Age of Aquarius
around the corner no this isn't I live
to see it probably this is like right
we're in the middle of a broad cultural
movement in the in change and
understanding in our relationship to the
world and really the scale that we need
to look at is century's technological
acceleration notwithstanding I found
that a really striking passage and that
sort of Young's take that we're going to
go through this age of fire and despair
and we're going to lose touch with lots
of the formative myths but that isn't
necessarily bad either right so so
breaking away from certain kinds of
myths right myths have a currency at a
particular time right the thing that was
sort of best fitted to human behavior in
the pre axial period it's not the same
thing that's fitted to human behavior
later and to some extent right we you
know we still see the rudiments of that
like when we talk about Joseph Campbell
and we talk about the hero's journey I
have to admit I'm deeply ambivalent
about the hero's and so he's always yeah
well I mean you know so Joseph Campbell
I think does you know he has the problem
that lots of structuralist have right
that he's not really paying attention to
the cultural specificity like that he
tends to over synthesize but that's not
what's interesting about it to me and
and this you'll see I think where this
connects to the way that Jordan I think
connects to some of this stuff too so
Joseph Campbell does this thing he
Chris the monomyth yeah the one guiding
you no myth that you can you know use
this the skeleton key to understand all
of this stuff okay fine so George Lucas
goes and reads the monomyth and he
expressly takes it and it's like I'm
gonna make a movie that's this combined
with Flash Gordon right and that's what
he does right so you know before that
George Lucas you're gonna get a bit of
rant here before that George Lucas had
made like you know thx 1-1 3-8 and
American Graffiti right and American
Graffiti made enough money that the
studio said George we're gonna give you
fifteen million bucks go make what you
want and he was like terrific I'm gonna
make this movie about skinny robots and
hairy giants and space wind sprints and
everybody looked at it and said or
whatever right and the cast thought it
was garbage
and everybody thought it was ridiculous
but he explicitly took the kind of like
incoherent massive notes that he had
instruction it according to Campbell and
what do we get coming out of the far
side we get the blockbuster and the
blockbuster is like that's a very modern
phenomenon in a certain kind of way
right the idea that people would go to a
movie theater and see something 12 times
that they would merchandise at that
level and scale the bedsheets the
lunchboxes and I'm old enough that I
remember the first wave of of Star Wars
here through right since then Disney has
learned to operate the pump full-time
but that first time through like it was
a phenomenon and to say that it you know
it's a structuring myth for people in my
generation I don't think it's an
exaggeration sure more people on the
British census identify themselves as
Jedi than Jewish yeah christen Philip
and I talked about that in the zombies
Yeah right okay so he's doing something
really specific when he taps into the
hero's journey and its enormous Lee
resonant for people you know there's a
sense that the older myths are kind of
played out right people don't get the
same kind of connection from them but
you take the same stuff and and reclose
it however since then Hollywood has done
what Western culture does right the
hero's journey as applied to Hollywood
blockbusters is the same thing that
we've done with fast food and cocaine we
take something that in it sort of like
occasional a non concentrated state is
good
for us and useful and instead turned it
into something that's delightful to the
degree of being poisonous we mainline
this same myth over and over and over
and over again and the problem with the
hero's journey in my opinion okay he
said it's just one myth it isn't to the
monomyth right it isn't the soul mythic
human beings tell or that's important to
structuring your life the sole thing
isn't about a descent and a struggle
against the great dragon that isn't the
only thing that's going on and we know
that even from young because young in a
pivotal time after his break both Freud
has this dream where he kills Siegfried
right Siegfried the solar Hillary kills
him and he feels tremendous shame but
what he interprets that dream for
himself right he's like oh right that
part of my life the solar hero part
where I am questing to fight dragons has
to come to an end if I am going to
develop wisdom right wisdom is not a
high energy state where you slay dragons
right right right right right right
excellent
right and so we we've sort of
selectively chosen to pull some of this
stuff right
that's a commodification and a
trivialization and all the way yeah and
also like a concentration we've made
these men as a good sense of the word
not in a good sense
no like a concentration like like I'm
using cocaine advisedly
you know you chew a few leaves of
cocaine it helps you with your altitude
sickness and it lets you March a little
longer and it's generally Pleasant you
take that and concentrate it to 50 or a
hundred times and it becomes addictive
compulsive or a numbing like all these
things that maybe are not so good so
this is actually you this is a very
maladaptive appropriation of young then
in some ways in some ways I think you
know and I I don't think I mean and I
want to get too much into corporate
criticism here but I don't think it's
coincidental Disney knows what they're
doing this is the having mode again oh
sure and look Disney has been you know
like buying up my childhood wholesale
they they own at all and they know what
they're doing Disney knows what they're
doing they understand this stuff they've
understood it for a long time right they
they understand how to make a meth tech
alright in this way but of course it's
not in the service to you know at the
end of the day maybe
we can look back fondly on Snow White in
the Seven Dwarves and say wow what a
wonderful cultural document that really
showed us da da da da da but does
anybody ultimately really believe that
about frozen - is frozen - being put out
like help us appropriate our own self
development certainly you've got a nice
space here so how does this no come back
to see that's a excellent critique of
Campbell Campbell in some ways like he
he's great in some ways he's great in
some ways but but nobody's denying them
yeah you're making it I think a very
strong but I think well argued criticism
that he's mouth shaping young in a
really you know a really important way
yes is that are you saying the same
thing about Jordan so some extent yes I
mean you know so I have known and worked
which were nearly as long as I've known
worked with you yes early contributor
from mine matters you know he and I had
looked at doing some projects we've
eaten meals together were on a
first-name basis yeah I've seen a lot of
his talks I know Jordan pretty well but
his particular take on certain aspects
of Jung is puzzling to me like it's just
I'm not totally sure how to square it so
there are some aspects of Jordan's
interpretation of Jung that I think are
terrific and straightforward right so
his emphasis on the importance and to
some extent the reality if not the
actuality of the mythic level of reality
is it's really central and crucial right
in that sense Jordan nails it right he
gets it it's like if you aren't paying
attention to this level of analysis
you're missing something really really
important and the fact that you kind of
that people want to point at it when
they're being sort of brass tacks
realists and saying like but what are we
really talking about here it's like no
that doesn't matter like you have to
interact with this you know you have to
interact with it for the same reason
that you know like an emotion can start
a war
but what our emotions really real it's
like yes if they are they're real right
and these patterns are real I mean to
give you just a quick example before I
go on this right it's like at some level
is the you know is the archetype of the
mother right as part of the collective
unconscious is that
a fundamental feature of reality well I
don't know but it's a fundamental
feature of every human psyche because
absolutely every human being had a
mother yeah and we all have some kind of
relationship two of them even if it's a
relationship of rejection
or absence or right and you know we've
talked about with like ducks Gosling's
right you know when they do imprinting
with Gosling's Gosling hatches out of
the egg and whatever is there at that
moment pretty much the Gosling will
imprint on and be disposed towards as
though was a mother so if it's a mother
goose
I said ducks if it's a mother goose in
the Gosling hatches that's what you know
nature expects in most conditions but
you could have a hand puppet or in some
cases a ping-pong ball and the Gosling
will imprint on the ping-pong ball in
precisely the same way the Gosling's got
a mother shaped hole or a goose shaped
hole right in its mind ready to be
filled by whatever appears in the moment
of imprinting and then it will you know
you roll the ball and the cousins will
waddle afterwards similarly we all have
that structure right okay so we have to
deal with these mythic realities right
that I think Jordan does really a
believe but there are other aspects of
Jung where his interpretation strikes me
as puzzling so for instance when he
talks about the shadow right you know
Jordan talks about the shadow quite a
bit and more often than not he talks
about the shadow sort of in its deep
collective sense and he references a
kind of note that that Jung made which
is like to really encounter the depths
of the collective shadow is a soul
blasting experience right so when we
talk about the shadow the shadow is sort
of everything that the ego rejects with
all the potentials within oneself that
we reject that we throw away they become
other so technically the shadow could be
filled with lots of virtues if you're a
particularly vicious person yes and in
fact it's typically filled with virtues
regardless right so Jung often talks
about the golden shadow the idea that
when you were doing shadow work in which
I mentioned is the apprentice piece
right a lot of what you're doing is yeah
partly that's about gaming a recognition
of the ways in which you have been
a bad person yeah but bad things that
you've done that you I you know people
that you've hurt bad things you've done
you kind of known it but a lot of it is
about just you know going back and
accessing the things that you left
behind right you made decisions you make
decisions about who you were going to be
and sometimes you made those decisions
because like you know your parents told
you to do one thing rather than the
other
sometimes you did it to differentiate
yourself from a sibling or a friend
right I'm this kind of person not that
kind of person it might just be might
just be underdeveloped aspects of
yourself then that's exactly what it it
is so so when we talk about shadow work
the golden shadow is pulling up these
things that you left behind that are
actually good because when you hit a
certain stage in life right you might
stagnate on the formulation that you
guys have and so where do you get that
material well you get it by reaching
back by reaching into the things you've
thrown away oh and there's difficulty
because you've set up a structure of
rejecting those things right right and
not just that but like typically
speaking to you know if you don't have
some kind of conscious relationship with
this part of yourself and most people
don't off the bat we reject it you tend
to take that material and project it
outside of yourself I said so you know
we're all familiar with the term like
love at first sight right ah but hate at
first sight yeah is the thing - right
the thing that makes love at first sight
operate is like we have an outsize
reaction a disproportionate degree of oh
my god I feel like I've known them
forever we wandered around it's like
we're soul mates that's all love at
first sight right right this feeling
that there is some depth there that
can't be there because we don't know
them as people but hate at first sight
operates - and it's deeply projected in
the same way right we encounter somebody
and we just they just drive us crazy
right we just hate their guts even
though we don't know mmm that's
projective shadow material shadow
material can also show up as like
incredible fear fear of the other right
so we reject and push away these things
it's sort of unthinkable it's so far
from us that it's unthinkable right and
there's a rigidity to that you know that
if you have that other ring I mean you
get kind of two problems that turn up in
the in sort of the clinical aspect of
this one
is you don't have access to that wealth
of possibilities right right so you
can't reach back and pull aspects of
yourself you know used to draw as a kid
I don't know I just lost track of that
it's very possible that to access sort
of the green shoots in your psyche for
your own development and it's necessary
to go and pull those things back but why
did you throw in a way to begin with
you might thrown it away because you got
chastised you need to grow up you know
grow up and stop drawing like you need
to focus on accounting or whatever right
right right
so that's part of the problem the other
part of the problem is the further away
you push it right the more you
dissociate yourself from that material
the more autonomous it becomes and so
the tendency is then for it to operate
sort of on its own it doesn't go away it
just does things and you don't notice
and you see this really clearly in
people that are I mean dissociative
right yeah where they've rejected some
aspect of themselves and so as an
example I knew a good friend of mine was
married to a fellow who was the first
instance that I ever encountered of what
I came to call Spock Buddhists so this
was a guy who who took up the Buddhism
and his explicit desire was to banish
all emotions from himself to become a
perfectly right and this is one of these
forms of spiritual bypassing brahman so
as a SPOC Buddhist this person believed
that he had no more emotions he believed
right so you can guess exactly what this
did what it meant was that he had these
incredible outbursts of sadness and rage
right but he could never own them it was
never him and always you yes this is a
rational response to what you're doing
they say this isn't me experiencing an
emotion this is the rational fitted
response to what you're doing this is
the problem with distancing yourself
from your shadow okay so doing shadow
work is the apprentice piece because
despite all the difficulty of really
looking taking a hard look in the mirror
and and acknowledging with sort of a
deep humility and
you know commitment to truth the ways in
which you are maybe not great right
which is part of the work it's also
right there it's easy to get at compared
to some of those deep psychic stuff also
the stuff those are the ways in which
you've been sort of an asshole yes right
are more easily accessible than these
we'll the one the the golden shadow is
that my understanding you to some extent
I mean the thing is that the ways in
which you've been an asshole generally
you know jump you at 2:00 in the morning
anyway right right the trink trick is
just not to shrink away right right we
we often most people will experience
some moments where we're like oh like I
feel profoundly bad about myself and you
know there are a few things that we can
do sometimes what we do is we sort of
slurp the kool-aid of self-esteem and
say no I'm perfect just as I am and
that's not good another thing that we do
is we externalize that outside of
ourselves these are the people that
become proponents of the one true way
and they're like I'm never wrong it's
always the world everybody's an idiot
all right these people who are always
right about everything and that's a
horrible inflexible place to be so I'm
trying to so what you're doing is making
an argument that the shadow is a very
complex thing yeah and our relationship
to it is also very complex absolutely
and then you you crafted this argument
and I think it's a really good argument
in response to my question about a
criticism of Jordan Jordan so so so one
aspect though of shadow work I've talked
about shadow work and I'm talking about
in very personal terms right but there
is an aspect that Jung talks about where
you're dealing with the shadow and the
collective sense and this is like
encountering some of the fundamental as
it were darkness that's part of the
human experience right for all that we
are you know spiritual beings concerned
but the esthetic and love we are also a
genocide 'el species right capable of
tremendous right producing tremendous
suffering cruelty like this is an aspect
of human experience - and one that
really does need to be confronted with
right it seems to me that a lot of the
time when Jordan talks about the shadow
he talks about it with a very strong
emphasis on that collective I see sense
right that you too could be a Nazi right
right and that's important it's
important to recognize that you could be
an
but you don't want to stay there all the
time you want to pull your focus back to
your personal shadow because that's
where the work is right right right
right so that's one thing but for
instance okay I saw a piece where
somebody had asked Jordan how one
develops their shadow right and leaving
aside that really properly in union
terms one doesn't develop their shadow
it develops all on its own just fine you
integrate it right you have a series of
encounters with it where you try to
render it conscious and develop a
relationship with it that it
specifically isn't project formed and so
he lays through a set of practices which
are like here is practically how you
would go about doing shadow work I was
very interested in this and so he says
something basically like you want to pay
attention to the moments where you were
experiencing resentment that was like
okay fair right negative negative
emotion is a good place to track and
then he moved from that to and that may
tell you when something is wrong in the
world and you want to stand up because
is an act of courage to oppose those
things okay and and then he sort of
rounded this out by referencing a young
quote that to engage in sort of an act
of radical honesty is can be as
effective in a certain sense right as as
doing psychoanalysis and so the idea is
that you track your own resentment that
tells you what's wrong with the world
and then you stand up you speak truth
against that thing and then he's a fine
recipe I think for an encounter with
your heroic self the courageous oppose
things you think are evil but that's not
shadow work oh right yeah the very
nature of that I mean it can't be shadow
work to identify something that you find
by activating an irksome in the world
and then denounce it that that's the
opposite right wrecker it's the opposite
in fact what you want to do is track
your resentment figure out what it is in
the world that's causing that right
that's that's triggering you the hopes
that are triggering you and then use
that to look within
and to figure out like what how am i
involved in this why is it triggering
for me so I give you an example this is
an example that it's interesting I teach
with and so it bounds us off
when I took my first young course at U
of T I was in the class and there was
this fellow in the class and every time
he spoke I experienced this really
strong like antipathy he drove me really
crazy he would talk about things and I
would find myself just simmering right
at the other side of the room thinking
to myself all this guy like such a
know-it-all like big deal like you know
about this you know I know about all
those things like like you really made
me man so much so that I used to come
home from that class and gripe to my
housemates I'd be like that guy was
talking again and like it really made me
nuts
but I was in a class on Union psychology
so I was also like mmm it seems like
this might be a shadow forever right you
know it seems like this might be a
shadow projection so instead what I did
was I approached him at the end serve at
the end of class and I said hi you know
I'm fine Anderson do you want to go get
a beer this person was one of my best
friends now hmm and one of the reasons
was all of the things that I was
reacting to in him are things I don't
like about myself mMmmm right it's like
I you know I have no illusions that I
both can come off and self-identify as
kind of a know-it-all in a motormouth
right and so to the extent that that's a
shadowy trait for me projecting it
outside and then having this like
irrational right feeling that tells you
more about shadow work the same goes for
the aspects of yourself just because it
appears monstrous doesn't mean that it
is monstrous if you approach it with
sort of uh you know a stance of charity
mmm you know you can think about this
with like the therapeutic work that
people use with nightmares and lucid
dreams right he does having a nightmare
where they're being you know chased by a
troll or something the idea is for them
to become sufficiently lucid that they
turn around and approach and turning
around and making the approach often
within the stuff right the the monster
will cease to be monstrous it will
transform and then you can actually talk
to it what do you want all I was just
trying to get your attention I've had
that experience right I mean
a standard trope that you see in dreams
if aspects of your mind can't get your
attention they've turned the dial up and
the main dial that they have access to
is horror right right so they keep
turning it up until you start having
nightmares and you pay attention right
but if you in fact make the approach
yourself all right we know generally
within psychotherapy making the approach
to an object of fear is different than
the object of the fear coming to you
yeah of course you get pounced on from
the bushes that's one thing you walk
into the cave it's something else yeah
so the idea is to make the approach
towards the object of your fear and
hatred and to try to charitably reframe
to see how you can form some
relationship with it and make it not so
bad right it's there's an aspect shift
involved so you know that's that's sort
of one example where you know the the
sort of recipe that Jordan gave on doing
shadow work is an interesting recipe
from the perspective of accessing one's
heroic you know like you know
mythological you know nature in some
sense that you've also emphasized we can
we can overemphasize that too right and
I think that that too is you know
something that may be a bit it's not
that I don't think that having us of
Warrior Ethos can't be a valuable part
of self-development but it's not the
only game in town yeah and so you know
similarly sometimes I you know Jordan
for instance we'll talk about order and
chaos and the DAO but then he has a
relatively sort of strident proactive
and externally focused approach to this
that doesn't strike me as particularly
Taoist at all right have courage act do
stuff yeah there's not there's a lot of
yang but not very much Yin
right exactly so to me both of those
things are sort of indicative of a
somewhat selective or you know I his
interpretation right it could be just as
good as mine and it's possible that he
has good supports for it but it's hard
to square in some sense how he deploys
that time and I don't think Jordan would
want to nor should his work be set up as
something that's beyond criticism it's
taken that way then
for me if people are reacting to it that
way then for me it loses any and all
intellectual respectability if people
are simply putting it beyond the pale of
criticism then that for me has exactly
the opposite effect it's like oh well
then I'm not going to take it seriously
right and why should I write this brings
me to dis prints me too actually sorry I
just want to say on that respect I mean
you know I've as I said I've talked to
Jourdan a lot and one of the things is I
mean of course he produces so many
lecturers so much material so many
classes right he does tend to orbit
themes but also the sheer amount of
stuff that he says means that
necessarily maybe there are certain
things that don't yeah right that's true
but but but on on the other hand that's
also something worthy of criticism
because if you're going to overwhelm
people with a large mass you have to do
a lot of work to render it
systematically coherent so that people
do have critical access to your work
right so I wanted to segue into
something so that criticism you made
because as you've noticed I sort of have
a criticism
whereas Jordan seems again there's the
mass of the work and I have to be
careful but I've seen a lot too
thank you yeah and many people are
taking it this way that young Jordan
seems to ally young with theism and
particularly with Christian theism in a
way that for many reasons that we
covered in our discussion seems to be me
deeply a mistake and I think you can
make a much stronger case that young as
a non theist and I think you can make a
much stronger case that he's a gnostic
and he's not a Christian and he's in
fact deeply critical at a fundamental
level of what what many people would
call Christianity yeah so I mean I've
tried to sort of square that off too and
partly as part of an effort to figure in
what sense Jordan's a Christian that's a
tortured question it is a tortured
question but but I think that maybe
there's something useful in there okay
like to the extent that he is drawing on
young as being like a central source
it's like okay so what are we saying
here we're saying that the myths of
incarnation and sacrifice and
resurrection
are still relevant right and I think
that's true I think that those things
are all true right and they think that
you know yes it's also true that you you
don't want to sort of you don't want to
just throw out the whole mythical
apparatus of your culture right like
there's just too much there and and in
the West we have done that somewhat you
know I a critique that I had many years
ago when we were talking about Buddhism
was I think far too many people in the
West have sort of sought the exotic ism
of right Eastern systems rather than
while they're going back to sort of try
to recapture some of that's nothing and
I understand why but right so I think if
if we take that level and just say yeah
yeah Christianity still has some useful
to borrow our language right some useful
ciphers ism yes right so you know in
that sense yeah I agree with you Jung's
not a Christian not in that sense not in
any kind of traditional conservative
sense
he had extremely like unorthodox
bordering on heretical and Gnostic views
and that doesn't mean that I don't think
that that material can't be used to
create a kind of regenerate right and I
think you know Tillich right there's a
reason tilaka gets accused to some
extent of the same thing there are lots
of people often called the heretic right
right because it's like in some sense
well what he's talking about this
doesn't seem to be our traditional
Sunday school material that's why I
think it's important to read Tillich the
way toward early does with young because
Tillich shows you somebody who more
explicitly tries to get this interacting
with Christianity and what a tough tough
job it is yes and how much the Christian
again he bends Christianity explicitly
to non-theism
right right and so that's yeah that's
the tackle but that was an argument I
wanted to make was there any other point
you wanted to bring up I mean there's
there's also stuff I've heard you
mention about sort of the treatment of
symbols that I seems to be implied but
what you've been saying here yeah I mean
you know there are a couple of angles
here
so so yeah one is that I periodically I
find and I think it may be that Jordan
himself doesn't think this like I think
it's a it's an outgrowth of rhetoric or
something but periodically there is a
way that he approaches symbolic
interpretation where his language isn't
tentative enough yeah so you see this so
sometimes in the biblical series where
he says this is the interim this is the
interpretation of XY said and I mean you
know there are versions of this I mean I
think at this point anybody that's
watched his material has seen you know
his unpacking of say the Garden of Eden
right which sort of mingles together
some speculative evolutionary ideas
about the development of color vision
snake patterning look fruit and a few
other things right into sort of a
general this is sort of a routine and
he's been you know he's been teaching
that routine it's part of it and I'm an
instructor to I understand what it's
like to have certain kinds of routines
you need them you need them so it's a
routine that he's been running since
Harvard you can go back and watch him
deliver some version of that talk in the
90s and the problem with it is that
because it's insufficiently tentative
people that don't have maybe the same
depth of experience in treating symbols
as being multi a spectral and
inexhaustible have a tendency to treat
that as a settled interpretation yes and
central to the notion of the symbol I
mean that's what distinguishes a symbol
from a sign yes exist sign means a thing
and a symbol means a lot of things like
and and sort of is endlessly disclosing
that is the whole point of it
that is why it's sacred that's why it's
useful yes right and and maybe even more
than that like you know the the the fact
that the symbol can endlessly disclose
in this way is part of what structure is
a bunch of other things in depth
psychology like there's a reason that
you can't have a book that's called ten
thousand dreams interpreted that's
serious because people always want that
they're like I saw Raven in my dream
what does it mean and the answer is like
well that depends right it's like you
take into account cultural levels you
take into account your personal history
you take into account your other dreams
things are never interpreted in
isolation they're always interpreted as
part of because there is a language that
develops and you know in keeping with
this like you know it's possible that
you are allowing these parts of your
psyche to plug in to certain kinds of
machinery you develop a relationship
when you're doing this kind of work
right where yeah you get better and
better at accessing deep layers of
yourself but also those layers start to
express things in certain ways I've
liked what I've been keeping a dream
journal for years right and I went
through union therapy and yeah did lots
of of course works and seminars and
stuff and I noticed that too you get
that that there's a dialogic feel
totally that comes out of it yeah
absolutely there's there's an exchange
back and forth and in some cases like
you know really it's funny because when
I was thinking about the the divine
double and the aspirational self it's
like a known quantity with sort of
analysts and therapists that soon after
you enter analysis you will often have
your first analyst dream where you you
write and that is often a really
important dream to pay attention to
because it's pointing towards some
future state of self like this is the
this is the kernel of what you're
developing anyway so sometimes I think
that the the sort of not taking a
sufficiently tentative line on some of
the stuff means that the the rhetoric of
of absolute interpretation enters in
yeah I agree with that and I see that's
to me where I don't know that well if if
you take the symbol as continually
disclosing that's much more Gnostic
right
whereas if you say this is the and this
is this is how the symbol is interpreted
that's ultimately just a just a
two-stage literalism yes right which is
which is I think deeply and antithetical
to Jung's approach to the symbol right
and so I actually think that that is to
some extent symptomatic of the other
trend that I sometimes see in Jordan's
work or at least in the sort of popular
approach to it which is the the
fetishization of certainty yes right so
you know there is a kind of line that
that runs through I think I first
encountered this when Jordan delivered a
talk called the necessity of virtue
which I saw number of years ago and it's
interest
I had the opportunity to sort of have
coffee and talk to him at length after
that talk where he had referenced fairly
heavily Dostoevsky and I ended up having
a conversation with him where I was like
okay yes all the stuff about virtue and
good and evil in the knowledge of good
and evil but Dostoyevsky also said
beauty will save the world yes and what
does that mean like how do you plug that
into what you're saying about truth and
good because that's the third one of the
triad and maybe the one that rescues us
because it's so much less fraught it's
less of a battleground right and
actually he had to be honest in person a
far more accommodating and right then
I'd been that was Jordan - yeah his
presentation at time that was I think
maybe the first conversation I ever had
with him so but but there is this
approach to certainty and then it goes
something like this right because you
know what to do at some level you know
what to do and you can tell when you
know what to do when you do what you
know no you do what you knew that you
had to do right because you feel a kind
of alignment and that's an interesting
idea and a seductive one I don't like
that idea as you know I I just don't
think it's true well that's why I don't
like it I think it's a dick either to
tribute that to kind of decadent
Romanticism so that's that's part of the
problem I mean I sort of run this idea
through and I think to myself well I
don't know what to do all of the time
and and and in Socrates sometimes didn't
didn't know what to do and it seems to
me that a great number of people
certainly in my practice either don't
know what to do or experiencing intense
ambivalence about what to do it can be
almost as horrible to choose between two
goods as two evils sure right and so you
know I think about this and I assume
somewhere in your series you talked
about like the way of the wanton and and
I like this yeah yeah yeah okay so I
think about this sometimes in that term
I think okay what is the most clarifying
life event that people often tagged on
to and one of the ones that you see come
up in clinical practice is a brush with
death people will pray for a brush with
death when they feel confused because it
will clarify their priorities right if I
couldn't if I can
scat really yep people are just like I
just want to get hit by bus and be put
in a body cast for six weeks so that I
will know what's really important that's
a thing people say so okay interesting
so I think about that I'm like okay I
brush with death we take that culturally
as being one of the most clarifying
things that we can have happen right but
there are two responses that you can
have to a brush with death and they
they're equally credible one is you can
say geez like I could get hit by a bus
tomorrow life is short
I need to stop focusing on endless
deferral I need to focus on the now you
know Yolo like I need to live my life
and start focusing on right that's one
response and we look at that and we say
yep that sounds that sounds very
plausible to me and then the other
response is crap I could get hit by a
bus tomorrow I really got to buckle down
I got to start thinking about the long
term yeah I got to stop frittering away
my long time in this day-to-day way and
really start considering legacy and we
think uh-huh and so what is it that
resolves that within the brush with
death where does certainty arrive I
don't know the brush with death is
supposed to provide it allegedly but I
don't believe that it does that this is
this is this is one of the central
points until it right right
the existential tone us we we most of
our life is we are facing things that
are in irresolvable tension with each
other of course I like that because of
maps on - relevance realization
machinery but independent of my
particular thing I think that's a
profound point that Tillich makes that
you know that that you know there is no
you know I need to be myself no no I
need to belong to a group no no I need
to be myself no I need and there is no
there is no fine there's no finally and
it and that means literally there is no
certainty about it that's right that's
right so so I you know and I'd like you
probably because of you at least in part
you know I I sure that like lots of
things are like evolution there isn't a
final form being a shark does not solve
every problem yeah sharks in the desert
by it the ultimate predator and them in
the trench but out in the desert they're
toast Tigers do well in the jungle they
do less well in the ice caps there is no
final
everything is about functional fit and
it's the same with the kinds of like
ontological strategies and essential
choices we make right so if that's the
case right then you know what to do it's
like no I don't think I do
and I don't think other people do either
and I think the sooner we we move away
from the idea that we have a certainty
that somehow were morally failing to
access the sooner we can deal with the
idea that we are fallible but that
doesn't let us off the hook no no in
fact demands that we interact with know
what I see you criticizing is is and I
say this in other context don't deify
any faculty don't demonize any faculty
that's right yes
and I think that that you could use that
as a union statement par excellence
right very much there are no demons well
that seems like a really good place I
think to try and draw it to a close I
think this was a extremely helpful to me
and you corrected me on some of the
sloppiness of my own thinking I thank
you for that and I think this will be a
tremendous value of people who are
interested in the meeting crisis young
Jordan Peterson thank you very much
thank you that was fun